Finding Aid for George W. Pray Papers, 1844-1890
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
George W. Pray Papers
1844-1890
Pray, George Washington, 1825-1890.
Physician; member of the first graduating class of the University of Michigan in 1845; papers include journals, correspondence, physician's records.
852080 Aa 2 mf235c
1.5 linear feet
1 oversize volumes
1 microfilms
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of the Pray family (Donor no. 4444 ), December 1993. A small addition to the collection came in 1998.
The collection is open for research. Researchers are required to use either the photocopy or microfilm copy of the Pray student journals.
Microfilm copies of the Pray student journals are available.
George W. Pray was born August 27, 1825 in Angelica, New York. He graduated from the University of Michigan in 1845 as a member of the first graduating class. He then enrolled at Western Reserve College where he received his medical degree in 1849. He practiced medicine first in Salem in Washtenaw County, Michigan (1849-1856), in Ronald Township in Ionia County (1856-1863), in Ann Arbor (1863-1867), and then back to Ionia County to his home near Woodard Lake. George Pray, in addition to his practice, also engaged in politics, serving his community as a Supervisor and as a member of the state House of Representatives (1879-1880). He died January 27, 1890.
The Pray collection includes journals, 1844-1849, covering his years as a student at the University of Michigan and in the Medical Department of Western Reserve College, Cleveland, Ohio. In addition, there is correspondence exchanged with his wife, Adele, primarily during the year 1879 when they were separated due to his service in the Michigan House. Other materials of interest include various personal and business account books and record books from his medical practice.
Subjects:
Democratic National Committee (U.S.); Democratic National Convention (1952: Chicago); Democratic National Convention (1956: Chicago); Democratic National Convention (1960: Los Angeles); Democratic National Convention (1964: Atlantic City, N.J.); Democratic Party (Mich.); Democratic Party (Mich.). State Central Committee.; Democratic Party (U.S.). Advisory Council.; Elections--Michigan--1948.; Elections--Michigan--1950.; Elections--Michigan--1952.; Elections--Michigan--1954.; Elections--Michigan--1956.; Elections--Michigan--1958.; Elections--Michigan--1960.; Elections--Michigan--1962.; Elections--Michigan--1964.; Elections--Michigan--1966.; Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.; Michigan Youth Commission.; Presidents--United States--Election--1952.; Presidents--United States--Election--1956.; Presidents--United States--Election--1960.; Presidents--United States--Election--1964.; Price, Margaret Bayne, 1912-1968.; United States. Congress--Elections, 1948.Elections, 1948.; United States. Congress--Elections, 1950.Elections, 1950.; United States. Congress--Elections, 1952.Elections, 1952.; United States--Politics and government--1945-1989.; Women in politics--Michigan.; Women in politics--United States.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Democratic National Committee (U.S.); Democratic Party (U.S.); Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978.; Jackson, Henry M. (Henry Martin), 1912-1983.; Johnson, Lady Bird, 1912-2007.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973.; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963.; Onassis, Jacqueline Kennedy, 1929-1994; Political elections.; Politics and government--1961-1970.; Stevenson, Adlai E. (Adlai Ewing), 1900-1965.; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972.; United States. Defense Advisory Committee on Women in the Services.; Women--Political life.
Contributors:
Acheson, Dean, 1893-1971.; Aiken, Paul C., 1910-1974; Albert, Carl Bert, 1908-2000; Anderson, Clinton Presba, 1895-1975; Anderson, Eugenie, 1900-; Bailey, John Moran, 1904-1975.; Ball, George W., 1909-; Bayh, Birch, 1928-; Bentley, Alvin M. (Alvin Morell), 1918-1969.; Berthelot, Helen W.; Bible, Alan, 1909-1988; Boggs, Thomas Hale, 1914-; Bowles, Chester, 1901-1986.; Brown, Edmund G. (Edmund Gerald), 1905-1996.; Bunker, Ellsworth, 1894-1984; Butler, Paul M. (Paul Mulholland), 1905-1961.; Cannon, Clarence, 1879-1964.; Cavanagh, Jerome Patrick, 1928-1979.; Celebrezze, Anthony J. (Anthony Joseph), 1910-1998; Church, Frank.; Clark, Joseph S.; Clay, Lucius D. (Lucius DuBignon), 1897-1978.; Clevenger, Raymond Francis, 1926-; Cohen, Wilbur J. (Wilbur Joseph), 1913-1987.; Collins, John J. (John Joseph), 1935-; Collins, LeRoy.; Connolly, John W.; Daley, Richard J., 1902-1976.; Dempsey, John N., 1915-; Diggs, Charles C.; Dillon, C. Douglas (Clarence Douglas), 1909-2003; DiSalle, Michael V. (Michael Vincent), 1908-1981; Douglas, Paul H. (Paul Howard), 1892-1976; Doyle, William F.; Duke, Angier Biddle, 1915-1995; Dunnigan, James P.; Edwards, India.; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969.; Farley, James A. (James Aloysius), 1888-1976.; Farrell, Lawrence Llewellyn, 1903-1971.; Faubus, Orval Eugene, 1910-1994; Ferency, Zolton A., 1922-1993; Fowler, Henry H., 1908-2000; Freeman, Orville L.; Galbraith, John Kenneth, 1908-2006.; Gore, Albert, 1907-1998.; Griffiths, Hicks G., 1910-; Griffiths, Martha W. (Martha Wright), 1912-2003.; Gronouski, John A. (John Austin), 1919-1996; Gruening, Ernest, 1887-1974.; Hannah, John A., 1902-1991; Harriman, W. Averell (William Averell), 1891-1986.; Harris, Fred R., 1930-; Hart, Adelaide, 1900-; Hart, Philip A. (Philip Aloysius), 1912-1976.; Hartke, Vance.; Hayden, Carl Trumbull, 1877-1972.; Hill, Lister, 1894-1984; Hobby, Oveta Culp, 1905-1995; Hodges, Luther Hartwell, 1898-1974.; Holland, Spessard L. (Spessard Lindsey), 1892-1971.; Hughes, Richard J. (Richard Joseph), 1909-1992; Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978.; Brown, Muriel Buck Humphrey.; Jackson, Henry M. (Henry Martin), 1912-1983.; Jeffrey, Mildred, 1911-2004.; Jenkins, Walter.; Johnson, Lady Bird, 1912-2007.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973.; Katzenbach, Nicholas deB. (Nicholas deBelleville), 1922-2012; Kefauver, Estes, 1903-1963.; Kefauver, Nancy Patterson.; Kennedy, Edward M. (Edward Moore), 1932-2009; Kennedy, Ethel, 1928-; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963.; Kennedy, Robert F., 1925-1968.; Kerner, Otto, 1908-1976.; Kerr, Robert S. (Robert Samuel), 1896-1963.; Lacy, Ernest J.; Lehman, Herbert H. (Herbert Henry), 1878-1963.; Lesinski, John, 1914-; Lippmann, Walter, 1889-1974.; Long, Russell B.; Lorch, Emil, 1870-1963.; Louchheim, Katie, 1903-1991; McCormack, John W., 1891-1980.; McGovern, George S. (George Stanley), 1922-2012; McIntyre, Thomas J., 1915-; McKeithen, John J. (John Julian), 1918-1999; McKellar, Kenneth Douglas, 1869-1957.; McKinney, Frank Edward, 1904-1974.; McNamara, Patrick Vincent, 1894-1966.; McNamara, Robert S., 1916-2009; Magnuson, Warren G. (Warren Grant), 1905-1989; Mansfield, Mike, 1903-2001; Mayo, Leonard W.; Mesta, Perle.; Mitchell, Stephen A. (Stephen Arnold), 1903-1974; Monroney, Mike, 1902-; Montoya, Joseph Manuel, 1915-1978; Moody, Blair, 1902-1954.; Morse, Wayne L. (Wayne Lyman), 1900-1974.; Moyers, Bill D.; Muskie, Edmund S., 1914-1996; Neuberger, Maurine B. (Maurine Brown), 1907-2000; O'Brien, Lawrence Francis.; Onassis, Jacqueline Kennedy, 1929-1994; Peabody, Endicott, 1920-1997; Peck, Gregory, 1916-; Powell, Adam Clayton, 1908-1972.; Proxmire, William.; Quimby, Thomas H. E. (Thomas Howard Emerson), 1918-1998; Rayburn, Sam, 1882-1961.; Reuther, Roy L., d. 1968.; Reuther, Victor G. (Victor George), 1912-2004; Reuther, Walter, 1907-1970.; Ribicoff, Abraham, 1910-1998; Roberts, Dennis Joseph, 1903-1994; Rockefeller, Laurance Spelman.; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962.; Roosevelt, Elliott, 1910-1990; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1914-1988.; Roosevelt, James, 1907-1991; Rusk, Dean, 1909-1994; Salinger, Pierre.; Sallade, George Wahr, 1922-; Sanford, Terry, 1917-1998; Scholle, August, 1904-; Smathers, George A. (George Armistead), 1913-2007; Sorenson, Theodore C.; Sparkman, John, 1899-1985.; Staebler, Burnette.; Staebler, Neil, 1905-2000; Stevenson, Adlai E. (Adlai Ewing), 1900-1965.; Swainson, John B. (John Burley), 1925-1994.; Symington, Stuart, 1901-1988; Talmadge, Herman E. (Herman Eugene), 1913-2002.; Todd, Paul Harold, 1921-2008; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972.; Tydings, Joseph Davies, 1928-; Tyroler, Charles.; Udall, Stewart L.; Vivian, Weston Edward, 1924-; Wagner, Robert F. (Robert Ferdinand), 1910-1991.; Weaver, Robert C. (Robert Clifton), 1907-1997; Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-1988.; Williams, G. Mennen, Mrs.; Williams, Harrison A.; Wirtz, Willard, 1912-2010; Yarborough, Ralph Webster, 1903-1996; Youngdahl, Luther W., 1896-1978
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Education: University of Michigan and Western Reserve College
  - Journals, June 1844-November 1849
    - Photocopies of Journals, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - Microfilm of Journals, 1 reels (Reel 1)
    - Original journals, 5 volumes (Box 2)
      [Restricted, for preservation reasons, researchers must use either the photocopies or microfilm.]
  - Loose page from journal (Box 1)
  - Partial typescript of journals, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Western Reserve College student notebooks and printed material, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Student essay (Box 1)
  - Expense log, 1849 (Box 1)
- Professional career
  - Various account books and physician's visiting log books, 1 folders (Box 1)
  - Financial daybook, 1849-1859 (Volume 1)
- Personal and estate material
  - Letters of George Pray to Adele Pray, 1879; 1881; 1889 (Box 1)
  - Letters of Adele Pray to George Pray, 1879 (Box 1)
  - Record book of the Woodard Lake Literary and Dramatic Association, 1879-1882 (Box 1)
  - Clippings about Pray family (Box 1)
  - Political advertisements and miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Inventory of library, 1906 (Box 1)
  - Pray estate agreements, 1863-1887 (Box 1)
  - Pray estate receipts, circa 1887 (Box 1)
  - Pray estate receipts, circa 1885-1899 (Box 1)
  - Pray estate receipts, circa 1895 (Box 1)
  - Receipts, circa 1896 (Box 1)
  - Registry, circa 1890 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, ephemera, receipts, etc (Box 1)
  - Published materials (Box 2)
    (cataloged copies available in printed collection)